Finding Aid for Vladimir Dedijer papers, 1881-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Miscellaneous Writings 1943-1987 (both published and unpublished)
  The Miscellaneous Writings series (1.2 linear feet) contains both published and unpublished materials authored by Dedijer between 1943 and 1987. Included here are articles; book outlines, drafts and research materials; contributions to other authors' works; Dedijer's doctoral thesis; examples of encyclopedia contributions; newspaper clippings; and reviews of other authors' works.
  - Articles
    - In English 1954-1970, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - In Other Languages 1943, 1951-1971, 1982 undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Book outlines, drafts and research materials
    - General 1959-1964, 1971, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Autobiographical projects
      - Confessions of a Biographer, 1978-1987, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Memoirs, 1954-1960 (Box 7)
      - Additional materials, untitled 1953-1971 (Box 7)
    - Beograde 1941 (Box 7)
    - Kiss of Death, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Neutrality and Neutralism; International Morality, 1961, undated (Box 7)
    - Revolution is the Only Way
      - Part I
        - "Introduction" (Box 7)
        - "Decline of English Football" (Box 7)
        - "England, 1935-1962" (Box 7)
      - Part II: "Egalitarianism in England" (Box 7)
      - Part III: "The Hands of English Housewives" (Box 7)
      - Part IV: "Outsiders in English Society" (Box 7)
      - Part V: "Materialism and Spiritualism in England?" (Box 7)
      - Part VI: "On English Snobbery" (Box 7)
      - Part VII: "British Educational System; Imperial Hangover" (Box 7)
  - Contributions to other authors' works
    - "A Comparative History of the European Resistance Movements", in Tito's war memoirs 1967 (Box 7)
    - "On Military Conventions: an essay on the evolution of international law," 1960 (Box 7)
    - "Randolph and the Yugoslav Partisans" in Randolph Churchill: the young pretender, 1970 (Box 7)
    - "What is the goal of a revolution?," introduction to the drama Whither, My Pretty Ones? by Bora Drenovac, 1957 (Box 7)
    - "Yugoslavia" in Legal Aspects of Foreign Investment, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Doctoral thesis
    - Thesis on the capitulation of the Yugoslav armed [forces] 1954, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Defense of thesis 1954-1957 (Box 7)
  - Encyclopedia contributions (examples of) 1959, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - In English 1956-1987, undated (Box 8)
    - In Other Languages 1953-1971, 1979 undated (Box 8)
  - Reviews of other authors' works
    - In English 1957-1971, 1983 (Box 8)
    - In Other Languages 1956-1957 (Box 8)
- Lectures and Speeches, 1948-1987
  The series Lectures and Speeches (.2 linear feet) is arranged chronologically and contains drafts and transcripts of many lectures and speeches presented by Dedijer during the years 1948 to 1987.
  - 1948
    - July 1948, Kongres Komunisticke Partije Jugoslavije (Box 8)
  - 1952
    - November 18, 1952, On the Right of Self-Determination, to the Third Committee of the General Assembly of the United Nations (Box 8)
    - November 21, 1952, Rad Generalne Skupstine oun Nepostovanje Prava na Samoopredeljenje Ugrozava Mir u Svijetu (Box 8)
  - 1956
    - August/September 1956, Peaceful Active Coexistence and International Law, to the International Law Association (Box 8)
  - 1957
    - June 3, 1957, Capitulation and Surrender in International Law (Box 8)
    - June 4, 1957 to the Foreign Affairs Committee of the Labor Party in the House of Commons (Box 8)
  - 1960
    - A Revised Role of the United Nations (Box 8)
  - 1961
    - April 28, 1961, Transformation of Russian Relations with Other Countries with the Special Reference to Eastern Europe, Africa, and Asia (Box 8)
    - June 1961, Welfare States and Their Economic Relations with Africa, Asia, and South America (Box 8)
    - November 1961, Similarities and Differences Between the Russian and Yugoslav Revolutions (Box 8)
  - 1962
    - January-February 1962, Lecture Series (9) on Evolution of Soviet Institutions and Law (Box 8)
    - October 22, 1962, Sino-Soviet Relations, to the Foreign Affairs Society, Copenhagen (Box 8)
    - October 25, 1962, The Methodology of the Study of Sino-Soviet Relations (Box 8)
    - November 8, 1962, Sino-Soviet Relations (Box 8)
    - November 1962-January 1963, Lecture Series (6) on The Idea of Revolution and the Organization of Revolutions (Box 8)
  - 1963
    - February 20, 1963, Some Reflections on Egalitarianism in a Contemporary Society (Box 8)
    - May 10, 1963, Is American Society Changing? (Box 8)
    - October 22, 1963, Ibsen and the Idea of Permanent Revolution--His Influence on the Young Bosnia Movement (Box 8)
  - 1964
    - Yugoslavia and the Non-Aligned Countries of Asia and Africa (Box 8)
  - 1965
    - January-May, 1965, Lecture Series, The Historian and Twentieth Century World Politics: the Responsibility for the Sarajevo Assassination 1914 (Box 8)
    - January 14, 1965, Could the Jews Have Resisted More Against the Nazi Extermination? (Box 8)
    - January 18, 1965, Peasantry in the Contemporary Revolutions (Box 8)
    - May 5, 1965, Symposium on the Responsibility of the Serbian Government for the Sarajevo Assassination (Box 8)
  - 1966
    - April, 1966, Hipoteze za Komparativno Zgodovino Odporniskih Gibanj v Evropi Med Drugo Svetovno Vojno (Box 8)
    - September, 1966, Economic Modernization and the Single Party System (Box 8)
  - 1987
    - November 19, 1987, Gorbachev and Historiography (Box 8)
- Audio and Visual Materials undated, 1927-1971
  The series Audio and Visual Materials (.8 linear feet) is divided into three subseries: Cartoons, Sketches, and Caricatures; Photographs; and Audiocassette Tapes. The Cartoons, Sketches, and Caricatures are few in number and generally date from the 1950s. The Photographs make up the bulk of this series and are separated into two groups, one group comprised of photographs taken by John Phillips, a photographer for Life magazine, and the other group containing all other photographs. The number assigned to each of the John Phillips photographs corresponds with the descriptions of the photographs located at the beginning of this group. The researcher should also be aware that the photographs taken by John Phillips are copyrighted by John Phillips. The three Audiocassette Tapes of an interview with Dedijer on his life experiences are closed.
  - Cartoons, Sketches, and Caricatures
    - Caricatures of Dedijer 1952 (Box 8)
    - Political cartoons (2) 1953, undated (Box 8)
    - Sketches of Dedijer (2) undated (Box 8)
  - Photographs
    - General
      - Bertrand Russell Tribunal (includes Bertrand Russell and Jean Paul Sartre; includes four color slides) 1966-1969, undated (Box 8)
      - Family and Friends
        - General 1938, 1954-1959, undated (Box 8)
        - Dedijer children 1957, undated (Box 8)
        - Dedijer, Olga 1937, 1940 undated (Box 8)
        - Dedijer, Vera 1947 (Box 8)
        - Rohde, Ina and Petar, Dedijers with undated (Box 8)
      - French Socialist Party 1951 (Box 8)
      - General of Dedijer (portraits, at work, giving speeches, etc.) 1945, 1948-1954, 1969 undated (Box 8)
      - Hungarians, Dedijer with 1947 (Box 8)
      - Jahonna (mostly skiing) 1953 (Box 8)
      - Kopaonik (skiing) 1954 (Box 8)
      - Military uniform, Dedijer in 1942-1945 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous groups of people with Dedijer (many identified) 1947-1952, 1971 undated (Box 8)
      - Paris Peace Conference 1946 (Box 8)
      - Politika (includes Milovan Djilas), 1951 (Box 8)
      - Studenica undated (Box 8)
      - Tito
        - General 1952-1953 (Box 8)
        - Burmese Delegation circa 1951 (Box 8)
        - Hunting 1951 (Box 8)
        - Indian Socialist Party 1952 (Box 8)
        - Progressive Socialist Party of Lebanon undated (Box 8)
      - United Nations 1948, 1953 (Box 8)
      - Zagreb 1948 (Box 8)
    - Taken by Life magazine photographer John Phillips (copyrighted by John Phillips)
      - Correspondence and description of photographs 1971 (Box 8)
      - Allied missions on island of Vis August 1944 (no. 15609) (Box 8)
      - Belgrade after its liberation November 1944 (no. 16999) (Box 8)
      - Danube Conference August 1948 (no. 27194) (Box 8)
      - A Day with Tito in his cave at Vis July 1944 (no. 15482) (Box 8)
      - Dedijer abroad June 1957 (no. 51580) (Box 8)
      - Dedijer-Djilas trial 1954 (no. 43900) (Box 8)
      - Dedijer in Cairo hospital 1943 (no. 14108) (Box 8)
      - Dedijer in Yugoslavia June 1954 (no. 43940) (Box 8)
      - Kruschev in Belgrade June 1955 (no. 45105) (Box 8)
      - May Day in Belgrade 1951-1952 (no. 30173) (Box 8)
      - Partisan Women in Italy May 1944 (no. 14867) (Box 8)
      - Partisans towing an LCI in the Adriatic August 1944 (no. 15607) (Box 8)
      - Slovenia and the Greater Reich October 1944 (no. 16155) (Box 8)
      - Tito at Okroglica, Slovenia September 1953 (no. 40416) (Box 8)
      - Tito in Bled August 1948 (no. 27324) (Box 8)
      - Tito in Greece June 1954 (no. 42363) (Box 8)
      - Tito in Turkey April 1954 (no. 41971) (Box 8)
      - Tito over the years 1950-1955 (no. 36896) (Box 8)
      - Tito returns to the Yugoslav mainland August 1944 (no. 15708) (Box 8)
      - Tito's generals April 1951 (no. 30170) (Box 8)
      - Trial of Draja Mikhailovich June 1946 (no. 21062) (Box 8)
      - Trieste October 1954 (no. 43210) (Box 8)
      - Yugoslav Partisans in Italy April 1944 (no. 14715) (Box 8)
      - Yugoslav refugees from Dalmatia in Egypt February 1944 (no. 14277) (Box 8)
      - Yugoslav state dinner for delegates of Danube Conference August 1948 (no. 27231) (Box 8)
      - Yugoslavia
        - 1949 (no. 30153), 2 folders (Box 8)
        - 1950 (no. 30163) (Box 8)
  - Audiocassette tapes
    - Interview with Dedijer regarding his life experiences undated, 3 sixty-minute cassette tapes (Box 8)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series (1.0 linear feet plus one outsize scrapbook) is divided into three subseries: Books and Journals; Leaflets and Broadsides; and Scrapbook. Books and Journals contains materials authored by Dedijer, materials relating to the Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals, and two autographed books about Jean Paul Sartre. The subseries Leaflets and Broadsides consists of leftist propaganda from the years 1935 to 1940 collected by Dedijer in his research. The Scrapbook includes correspondence and newsclippings, the majority of it relating to Tito and Dedijer's biography of him, and covers the years 1947 to 1953.
  - Books and Journals
    - Contat, Michel and Michel Rybalka. Les Ecrits de Sartre: chronologie bibliographie commentee, 1970 (Box 9)
      (autographed by Sartre)
    - Crimes de Guerre au Vietnam, cahier no. 2 (published by Centre International d'Information pour la Denonciation des Crimes de Guerre), 1969 (Box 9)
    - Dedijer, Vladimir. Dnevnik: 1941-1944, 1970, 3 volumes (Box 9)
    - Dedijer, Vladimir. Sarajewo 1914, 1984, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Dedijer, Vladimir and Rudolf Rizman. Universal Validity of Human Rights: an interdisciplinary analysis, the case of Russell Tribunals, 1982 (Box 9)
    - KOMYH CT: OP AH EHTPA HO KOM TETA CABE A KOMYH CTA JY OC AB JE
      - BPOJ 1-2 January-February 1954 (Box 9)
      - BPOJ 4 April 1954 (Box 9)
    - Sendyk-Siegel, Liliane. Sartre: images d'une vie, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Sodobnost: Vietnam, Leto XVI, Stevilka 5, 1968 (Box 9)
    - The Spokesman
      (founded by Bertrand Russell and includes articles by Dedijer)
      - May 1970 Number 3 (Box 9)
      - August / September 1971 Numbers 15-16 (Box 9)
    - Tribunal Russell 2: le jugement final, 1968 (Box 9)
      (Preface by Dedijer)
    - Russelltribunalen: fran sessionerna i Stockholm och Roskilde, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Raselov Sud: sudenje u Stokholmu i zavrsno sudenje u Kopenhagenu, 1967 (Box 9)
  - Leaflets and Broadsides
    - Jovanovic, Dragoljub, materials of (leader of the Peasant Left) 1935-1940 (Box 9)
    - Young Communists and similar organizations 1935-1940 (Box 9)
    - Yugoslav AntiMarxist Committee bulletin March 1938-January 1940, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook 1947-1953 (Volume 1)